Guide to the Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. Cambodia Witness Exhibit,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. Cambodia Witness Exhibit,
1981-1987
Amnesty International USA. Cambodia Witness Exhibit.
1 Linear Foot (52 Photographs, 1 Map, and 2 Files in 3 Oversized Boxes; Text Panels in 1 Oversized Box)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY. 10027
6269848
The collection includes 52 photographs and a map that were part of the Cambodia Witness Exhibit (1983). It also includes the exhibit brochure, catalog list, and a file on the exhibit from its coordinator, Joan Libby. The photographs were taken by David Hawk during two trips to Cambodia in March 1981 and April 1982. The exhibit includes images of the prison at Tuol Sleng, prisoners (from existing files), survivors, mass graves, and the destruction of temples and churches.
Historical Note
Amnesty International (AI), a non-governmental organization (NGO), was founded in 1961 to campaign for internationally recognized human rights. In its early years, the main focus of AI's campaigns was to free prisoners of conscience. Within a short time, its mandate expanded to include campaigning for prompt and fair trails for all political prisoners, to end extrajudicial executions and disappearances, and to abolish the death penalty, torture and other cruel treatment or punishment. The organization also works to bring perpetrators of these abuses to justice in accordance with international standards.
Amnesty International of the USA, Inc. (AIUSA) is the United States section of Amnesty International. AIUSA was incorporated in 1966. The section is governed by a Board of Directors. The work of the section is carried out through the national office, regional offices, networks, country specialists (co-groups), student groups and local groups.
The photographs for the Cambodia Witness Exhibit were taken by David Hawk during two trips to Cambodia in March 1981 and April 1982. Hawk had worked on Cambodian relief and refugee issues while based in Bangkok, Thailand during 1980-1981. Hawk later became the Director of the Cambodian Documentation Commission in the mid-1980s and directed the Cambodia Office of the U.N. High Commissioner for Human Rights in the 1990s. He has also been involved in other human rights issues
The Cambodia Witness Exhibit was organized and sponsored by Amnesty International USA, of which David Hawk is a former executive director (1974-1978), and was first shown in Washington D.C. in April 1983.
Scope and Content
The bulk of the collection consists of both black & white and color photographs used in the Cambodia Witness Exhibit (1983).
The first series contains two paper files of material related to the exhibit. The first file contains the exhibit brochure and the catalog list of exhibit materials. The catalog list includes a number, title and caption for all exhibit items, except for three "optional" photographs of executed prisoners and a map of Cambodia. The second file contains documentation on the exhibit kept by its coordinator, Joan Libby. Other files on the Cambodia Witness Exhibit may be found in other record groups of the archives of Amnesty International of the USA, Inc.
The second series contains the exhibit material. The photographs are filed using the titles, numbers and original order described by the exhibit's catalog list. The three "optional" exhibit photographs and the map are filed last.
The photographs document several subjects: Tuol Sleng (Images of the interior and exterior of the prison); prisoners (Images of entry photographs and of executed prisoners taken from existing records in Cambodia); survivors (Images include surviving prisoners, Buddhist monks and nuns, and Cham, an ethnic minority); mass graves and memorials (Images of sites at Cheung Ek, Tonle Bati, Ta Mon, and Siem Reap); and destroyed religious buildings (Images are predominantly of destroyed Buddhist temples. There is one image of the site of a destroyed Catholic cathedral).
The exhibit text panels will be scanned and copies included in the collection for use and reference.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series:
Series 1: Files on the Exhibit
Series 2: Exhibit Materials
Subjects
Amnesty International USA.; Party of Democratic Kampuchea.; Tuol Sleng (Prison: Phnom Penh, Cambodia); Hawk, David R.; Cambodia--History--1975-1979.; Cambodia--Politics and government--1975-1979.; Extrajudicial executions--Cambodia.; Human rights--Cambodia.; Mass burials--Cambodia.; Memorials--Cambodia.; Prisoners--Cambodia.; Prisons--Cambodia.; Photographic prints
Access Restrictions
This collection is located on-site.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
Joan Libby; Donation; March 2007 accn number
The material was originally deposited at the University of Colorado at Boulder by Amnesty International USA's National Office in the 1990s. The material was deposited with the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Columbia University in February 2006. The exhibit coordinator's file on the exhibit was donated to the library by Joan Libby in March 2007.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series I: Files on the Exhibit, 1981-1987
  - Exhibit Brochure and Catalog List, 1983 (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 1)
  - Exhibit Coordinator's File on the Exhibit, 1981-1987 (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 2)
- Series II: Exhibit Materials, 1983
  - CAT #1--Angkor Wat (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 1)
  - CAT #2--Cheung Ek Enclosure--Top Down View (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 2)
  - CAT #3--Three Young Women (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 3)
  - CAT #4--Blindfolded Skulls (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 4)
  - CAT #5--Entry Photo (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 5)
  - CAT #6--Barbed Wire (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 6)
  - CAT #7--Tuol Sleng Exterior (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 7)
  - CAT #8--Photograph of Painting (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 8)
  - CAT #9--Entry Photo (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 9)
  - CAT #10--Body on Stretcher (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 3)
  - CAT #11--Tuol Sleng Hallway (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 4)
  - CAT #12--Tuol Sleng Interior (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 10)
  - CAT #13--Leg Irons (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 5)
  - CAT #14--Cell Interior (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 6)
  - CAT #15--Interrogation Room (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 11)
  - CAT #16--Executed Prisoner (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 7)
  - CAT #17--Mr. Ung Pech (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 12)
  - CAT #18--Documents (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 8)
  - CAT #19--Executed Prisoner 24-9-77 (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 9)
  - CAT #20--Executed Prisoner 11-10-77 (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 10)
  - CAT #21--Tonle Bati Mass Grave (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 13)
  - CAT #22--Tonle Bati Detail (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 14)
  - CAT #23--Mr. Mom Chhot (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 11)
  - CAT #24--Tonle Bati, 1982 (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 15)
  - CAT #25--Cheung Ek Grave Pits (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 16)
  - CAT #26--Cheung Ek, 1982 (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 17)
  - CAT #27--Cheung Ek Enclosure (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 18)
  - CAT #28--Ta Mon Mass Grave (Box Flat Box 746, Folder 19)
  - CAT #29--Mrs. Ieng Sopheong Survivor (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 12)
  - CAT #30--Kampot Grave (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 1)
  - CAT #31--Siem Reap Mass Grave (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 2)
  - CAT #32--Cham Survivors (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 3)
  - CAT #33--Buddhist Survivors (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 4)
  - CAT #34--Ampil Bey Destroyed Temple (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 5)
  - CAT #35--Monks Quarters Destroyed (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 6)
  - CAT #36--Catholic Cathedral Site (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 13)
  - CAT #37--Cham Survivors Seated (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 7)
  - CAT #38--Destroyed Temple Takeo (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 8)
  - CAT #39--Destroyed Library (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 9)
  - CAT #40--Monk and Buddha Head (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 14)
  - CAT #41--Buddha Head (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 10)
  - CAT #42--Tep Rang Sey Temple/Warehouse (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 11)
  - CAT #43--Pichey Udong Temple/Destroyed (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 15)
  - CAT #44--Mr. Heng Chor and Family (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 12)
  - CAT #45--Buddhist Nuns (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 13)
  - CAT #46--Tuol Sleng (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 14)
  - CAT #47--Prisoner Photos on Wall Tuol Sleng (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 15)
  - CAT #48--Cheung Ek Enclosure/Skulls (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 16)
  - CAT #49--Tonle Bati, 1982 (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 17)
  - Optional Exhibit Photograph--Executed Prisoner (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 18)
  - Optional Exhibit Photograph--Executed Prisoner (Box Flat Box 745, Folder 16-17)
  - Map--Vietnam; Laos and Cambodia (Box Flat Box 747, Folder 19)
    (This map was framed over a duplicate copy of an exhibit photograph. It is not listed in the Catalog List.)
  - Exhibit Text Panels (Box 4)